The cell cycle is a highly regulated series of events that lead to cell growth and division.
It is divided into distinct phases: G1 (cell growth), S (DNA synthesis), G2 (preparation for mitosis), and M (mitosis).
During the G1 phase, the cell grows and accumulates resources necessary for DNA replication.
In the S phase, the entire genome is replicated, ensuring each daughter cell receives a complete set of chromosomes.
The G2 phase involves further growth and preparation, where the cell checks for DNA errors before division.
Mitosis, the M phase, is where the cell’s nucleus divides, followed by cytokinesis which splits the cytoplasm.
Cell cycle checkpoints act as quality control, ensuring DNA is replicated correctly and damage is repaired.
Failures in these regulatory checkpoints can lead to uncontrolled cell division and cancer.
Modern research explores cell cycle regulators to develop targeted therapies for cancer and other diseases.
The study of the cell cycle not only provides insight into cellular function but also underpins many advancements in biomedical science.