DNA, or deoxyribonucleic acid, is the fundamental molecule that carries genetic information in all living organisms.
It is composed of two long strands forming a double helix, a structure first described by Watson and Crick.
The strands are made up of nucleotide bases: adenine, thymine, cytosine, and guanine, which pair specifically.
DNA replication ensures that genetic information is faithfully copied before cell division occurs.
Mutations can occur during replication or due to environmental factors, affecting the sequence and function of genes.
Cells have intricate repair mechanisms to correct errors, maintaining the integrity of the genome.
Gene expression involves transcription of DNA into RNA, which is then translated into proteins that perform cellular functions.
Genetic diversity arises from processes like recombination and mutation, driving evolution and adaptation.
Modern biotechnology uses DNA sequencing and genetic engineering in fields such as medicine, agriculture, and forensic science.
Understanding DNA has revolutionized biology, leading to breakthroughs in diagnostics, treatment, and personalized medicine.