Enzymes are biological catalysts that accelerate chemical reactions essential for life.
They lower the activation energy required for reactions, making processes efficient and fast.
Each enzyme has a specific active site where it binds to its substrate in a lock-and-key mechanism.
The enzyme-substrate complex facilitates the conversion of substrates into products through various biochemical reactions.
Enzyme kinetics, including reaction rates and affinity for substrates, are influenced by temperature and pH levels.
Inhibitors can affect enzyme activity; competitive inhibitors block the active site while non-competitive inhibitors bind elsewhere.
Enzymes play vital roles in metabolic pathways, including digestion, energy production, and cellular signaling.
They are also used in industrial applications such as food processing, biofuel production, and pharmaceutical manufacturing.
Understanding enzyme function and regulation has led to advances in medicine, including drug development and disease treatment.
Overall, enzymes are critical for sustaining life and driving the biochemical processes that occur in every cell.