The nervous system is a complex network responsible for transmitting signals and coordinating actions in the body.
It is divided into the central nervous system (CNS), comprising the brain and spinal cord, and the peripheral nervous system (PNS).
Neurons, the primary cells of the nervous system, transmit electrical impulses through specialized structures.
Synapses are the junctions where neurons communicate with each other via chemical messengers known as neurotransmitters.
The brain processes complex information, controlling voluntary actions, emotions, and cognitive functions.
The spinal cord acts as a conduit, relaying signals between the brain and the rest of the body.
The PNS includes sensory nerves that transmit external stimuli and motor nerves that control muscle movements.
Neurotransmitters such as dopamine, serotonin, and acetylcholine are crucial for mood regulation and neural communication.
Disorders of the nervous system, including Alzheimer's, Parkinson's, and epilepsy, impact millions worldwide.
Ongoing research in neuroscience continues to uncover the complexities of neural networks, offering new insights into treatment and rehabilitation.