Climate change refers to long-term changes in temperature, precipitation, and weather patterns.
It is primarily caused by human activities such as burning fossil fuels, deforestation, and industrial emissions.
The greenhouse effect plays a major role, where gases like CO2 trap heat in the Earth's atmosphere.
Global temperatures have risen by about 1.2°C since pre-industrial times, leading to ice caps melting and sea levels rising.
Rising sea levels threaten coastal cities, leading to displacement of populations and loss of habitat.
Extreme weather events such as hurricanes, droughts, and wildfires have become more frequent due to climate change.
Efforts to combat climate change include reducing carbon emissions, shifting to renewable energy, and conservation projects.
International agreements such as the Paris Agreement aim to limit global warming to below 2°C.
Sustainable development and green technologies play a crucial role in mitigating climate change.
Everyone can contribute by reducing waste, using public transport, and supporting eco-friendly initiatives.