A continent is a large continuous mass of land conventionally regarded as a collective region.
There are seven continents on Earth: Asia, Africa, North America, South America, Antarctica, Europe, and Australia.
Asia is the largest and most populous continent, home to over 4.5 billion people.
Africa is rich in natural resources and has diverse ecosystems ranging from deserts to tropical rainforests.
North America includes countries such as the United States, Canada, and Mexico, and features diverse geography from tundras to tropical regions.
South America is home to the Amazon Rainforest, one of the most biodiverse places on Earth.
Antarctica is the coldest continent and is covered almost entirely by ice, making it the least inhabited region.
Europe is known for its rich history, economic development, and cultural diversity.
Australia, the smallest continent, is unique for its distinct wildlife, including kangaroos and koalas.
Continents have evolved over millions of years due to plate tectonics, which continue to shape the Earth's surface.