A river is a natural flowing watercourse, usually freshwater, flowing towards an ocean, sea, lake, or another river.
Rivers play a crucial role in shaping landscapes through erosion and deposition.
Major rivers such as the Amazon, Nile, and Mississippi are vital for transport, irrigation, and ecosystems.
Rivers have different stages: young (steep and fast), mature (wider and moderate flow), and old (slow-moving with meanders).
Deltas form where rivers meet larger bodies of water, depositing sediments and creating fertile land.
Floodplains, created by rivers, provide nutrient-rich soil but are prone to flooding.
Dams and reservoirs are built on rivers for hydroelectric power, water storage, and flood control.
Pollution and climate change have negatively impacted rivers, affecting biodiversity and freshwater availability.
Rivers are essential for sustaining wildlife, agriculture, and human civilization.
Conservation efforts focus on protecting river ecosystems and reducing pollution to ensure clean water supply for future generations.