A volcano is an opening in the Earth's crust that allows molten rock, ash, and gases to escape.
Volcanoes are found in tectonically active regions, mainly along the Pacific Ring of Fire.
There are different types of volcanoes: shield, stratovolcanoes, cinder cone, and caldera volcanoes.
Eruptions can be explosive or effusive, depending on magma composition and pressure buildup.
Volcanic eruptions can cause devastating impacts such as lava flows, ash clouds, and tsunamis.
Volcanic activity plays a role in shaping landscapes and enriching soil with minerals, making it fertile for agriculture.
Some famous volcanoes include Mount Vesuvius, Mount St. Helens, and Mauna Loa.
Monitoring systems help predict eruptions using seismic activity, gas emissions, and ground deformation.
Volcanic islands such as Hawaii were formed due to hot spot volcanic activity.
While dangerous, volcanoes also provide geothermal energy, which is harnessed for electricity in some regions.